Felix Lucka

Curriculum Vitae

Personal Information

Born in Hannover, Germany on May 23, 1985, nationality: German

email f.lucka@ucl.ac.uk

homepage felixlucka.github.io

Research Interests

Theoretical Inverse problems, Bayesian inference, variational regularization, compressed sensing, mathe-

matical modeling

Methodical MCMC, computational optimization, numerics for PDEs

Applications Biomedical imaging and computing, neuroscience

Work Groups

since 2014 **Member of 'The Center for Medical Image Computing'**, Department of Computer Science, University College London, supervisor: Prof. Dr. Simon Arridge.

2013 **Research Visit to UCLA**, *Department of Mathematics*, invited by Prof. Dr. Andrea Bertozzi and Prof. Dr. Stanley Osher.

2010-2014 **Member of 'Workgroup Imaging'**, *Institute of Computational and Applied Mathematics, University of Münster*, headed by Prof. Dr. Martin Burger.

2008-2014 Member of "SIM-NEURO: Stimulation, Imaging and Modeling of NEUROnal networks in the human brain", Institute for Biomagnetism and Biosignalanalysis, University of Münster, headed by PD Dr. Carsten H. Wolters.

Five Key Publications

- [1] M. Burger and F. Lucka. Maximum a posteriori estimates in linear inverse problems with log-concave priors are proper Bayes estimators. *Inverse Problems*, 30(11):114004, 2014.
- [2] F. Lucka. Fast Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling for sparse Bayesian inference in high-dimensional inverse problems using L1-type priors. *Inverse Problems*, 28(12):125012, 2012.
- [3] F. Lucka, S. Pursiainen, M. Burger, and C.H. Wolters. Hierarchical Bayesian inference for the EEG inverse problem using realistic FE head models: Depth localization and source separation for focal primary currents. *NeuroImage*, 61(4):1364–1382, 2012.
- [4] S.R. Arridge, P. Beard, M.M. Betcke, B. Cox, N. Huynh, F. Lucka, O. Ogunlade, and E. Zhang. Accelerated high-resolution photoacoustic tomography via compressed sensing. *Physics in Medicine and Biology*, 61(24):8908, 2016.
- [5] S.R. Arridge, M.M. Betcke, B.T. Cox, F. Lucka, and B.E. Treeby. On the adjoint operator in photoacoustic tomography. *Inverse Problems*, 32(11):115012, 2016.

PhD Thesis

Title Bayesian Inversion in Biomedical Imaging

Supervisors Prof. Dr. Martin Burger and PD Dr. Carsten H. Wolters

Reviewers Prof. Dr. Martin Burger, Prof. Dr. Samuli Siltanen and PD Dr. Carsten H. Wolters

 $Sub./Defense \quad Dec.\ 2014\ /\ 23.01.2015$

Degree summa cum laude

Permalink http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:hbz:6-80359613770

Scientific Activities

Symposia Applied Inverse Problems, Hangzhou, 2017: New tricks for old problems: Novel computational methods for inverse problems.

SIAM Imaging Science, Albuquerque, 2016: *Imaging in the fast lane: in pursuit of dynamical information.*

Applied Inverse Problems, Helsinki, 2015: Bayesian Computation.

Reviewer Biomedical Physics & Engineering Express, Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, Computational Statistics and Data, IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging, IEEE Transactions on Image Processing, Inverse Problems, Inverse Problems and Imaging, Inverse Problems in Science and Engineering, Journal of Biomedical Optics, Journal of Optics, Journal of the Optical Society of America A, Mathematical Problems in Engineering, NeuroImage, Neuro

logical Research, Optics Express, SIAM Journal on Imaging Sciences, SPARS.

Referee German National Academic Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes), University of Innsbruck, Austria.

Teaching

since 2015 Teaching assistant for the lecture Inverse Problems in Imaging

2013 Introductory course to Matlab

since 2012 Supervision of Bachelor and Masters theses.

2009–2010 Student tutor for an exercise for the course Stochastics

2007–2008 Student mentor for the courses Theoretical Physics III and IV

Education

2005-2011 **Studies in Mathematics with minor in Physics**, *University of Münster*, grade of diploma: 0.85 (with greatest distinction).

2006-2011 **Studies in Physics with minor in Computer Science**, *University of Münster*, grade of intermediate diploma: 1.0.

1995–2004 **Secondary education (Abitur)**, Gymnasium Mellendorf, final grade: 1.0.

1991–1995 **Primary education**, *Grundschule Bissendorf*.

Awards and Scholarships

- Apr. 2014 Poster price, bbs2014, Berlin.
- Okt. 2012 Poster price, NeuroVisionen 8, Aachen.
- Apr. 2012 **Best talk in "Biomagnetism and online signal processing"**, Workshop "Innovative Verarbeitung bioelektrischer und biomagnetischer Signale" bbs2012, Berlin.
- Sep. 2011 **Research visit funding**, Funding for a two week research visit at the RTWH Aachen by the annual meeting of the DMV (German mathematical society).
- 2011-2014 **PhD-Scholarship**, German National Academic Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes).
- 2005-2011 **Scholarship**, German National Academic Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes).

Experience

- since 2014 Research associate, Department of Computer Science, University College London.
- 2012-2014 Research assistant, Institute for Computational and Applied Mathematics, WWU.
- 2009–2010 Student assistant, Institute of Mathematical Statistics, WWU.
- 2008–2009 **Student assistant**, Institute for Biomagnetism and Biosignalanalysis, WWU.
- March 2008 Internship, Max-Planck-Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization, Göttingen.
 - 2007–2008 Student assistant, Institute for Theoretical Physics, WWU.
 - 2004–2005 **Alternative civilian service (Zivildienst)**, gemeinnützige Gesellschaft für integrative Sozialdienste mbH (GIS), school escort for a disabled child.

Engagement

University Students' union (Fachschaft), faculty council (Fachbereichsrat), miscellaneous faculty committees, faculty task force *Public Relations*, faculty task force *Networking*, organizer of the

Lange Nacht der Mathematik (Long Night of the Sciences for mathematics), co-organizer of

the awarded project Studies an die Schulen

Gymnasium Student council (Schülervertretung), school president (Schülersprecher)

Miscellaneous Local youth council (Jugendparament der Gemeinde), miscellaneous political activities

References

Felix Lucha

Prof. Dr. Simon Arridge: s.arridge@cs.ucl.ac.uk

Prof. Dr. Martin Burger: martin.burger@uni-muenster.de

Prof. Dr. Samuli Siltanen: samuli.siltanen@helsinki.fi

London.

January 21, 2017